I'm Roque Fernández Alcañiz
and I come from Galicia, Spain, and I’m
here to present my paper, AI-generated
code + E-Poetry: Exploring the
possibilities of digital poetry
with AI generated code in TouchDesigner.
So I wanted to start
with this quote by the author Lovelace,
in which she
talks already about the possibility,
the possibilities of her poetic science
or her poetic mathematics, to integrate
art code in that time, and mathematics
to create a musical compositions
or visual compositions.
And that's
what we are going to be seen today.
And because I don't want to lose sometime
I will be going forwards.
So I work with a hypothesis
that the rapid increase
in artificial intelligence programing
capabilities
and the existence of multimedia content
creation applications that enable
the integration of such generative code
significantly stunted avenues
for accessible creation
of experimental digital art and digital
literacy, contemporary digital art
and contemporary digital poetry. And.
We'll be focusing on touch Designer
that is applied by derivatives
and published, I think, in 2008.
And it's a novel
visual programing software.
You can see here
a screenshot of the user interface.
And it's really used basically
to create multimedia creations
and live video performances.
And apart from that,
I have other objectives that are of course
learned some Python
and some touch designer and
avoid as much technical debt as possible
because like technical debt,
is that knowledge that we get
when we used a lot of AI basically,
and we use AI as a shortcut
to other processes
that would get us that knowledge.
And also,
I would like to allude a workflows
that include big corporations
like anthropic or OpenAI
because of privacy and some compromise
with open source software.
And then I have here the methodology.
The first section will be academic.
I will introduce
some some poets that work
with generated code
and also with a with digital poetry.
And after that
I will be making a practice based research
in which I will try myself to create
a digital poem made in Tulsa.
And with the use of generative code
made by an AI.
And lastly, the final reports.
So my framework is
is not really complex.
I have as a reference the the works,
the words and works
by de Rosario
and her definition of poetry.
And also I'm supported
by a whole bunch of really established
authors in the matter
and in the field of digital poetry studies
and for artificial intelligence,
I only work with a critical
and digital humanities
approach and also critical AI approach.
For example, here the references
their recent reference of ministry
and impossibility, and with that spirit
of defending the use of AI,
but as a tool, as Loveless said
and about the center,
I cannot say anything more.
It's a really complicated software is
it is stated like that and the, the,
the proper derivative.
The company that holds talks
designer states that.
So here we have the classification
of digital points made that Rosario.
It has to access the classification
of the points
under morphological semiotic categories
and according to their reading practice.
So it's a really comprehensive
classification that still
today has a use.
And here we have the three artists
that we are going to check.
The first one
is the engineer cut song system
in Living and Simulated systems, and
basically Gemini AI with support
even from Google Labs
to create her compositions.
He also she also uses a lot of the media
type plugin.
And I have here
two screenshots of her work.
Strange flowers of the mind
are blossoming
silently under a fast and untitled
first one.
I'm not, I'm not sure of.
I'm not sure if.
See you said the code so I'm not sure.
But the second one, untitled,
the one in the top right.
See, stays in the description of her work
that she used gaming.
Gemini.
And and it's a video that
if we had more time, we put in that
two extra minutes, we would see.
It's a video that
in which we can see here
moving her hands and resizing continuously
that that takes that we can see here.
And, and it would be a segmented based
with a primary exploratory
reading practice.
Then we have Gomez Santana.
Her real name is Natalia Herrick.
And she is also a digital
artist
that works mainly with touch designer
and with intelligence
artificial intelligence tools.
And I chose her work also
on that work
that she uploaded to her TikTok.
And that we can see in the top right
picture.
And it's also a video.
In the video,
she uses a Midi controller to permute
and to move all those letters and words
that we can see here.
So it's also like
a really interesting piece of art
to see and to try and explore.
And then we have Okami
for a visualization.
He is an artist and educator.
And he he didn't
create like the digital poem by by itself,
but he had a plugin
that is given that you can use
in Touch Designer, and it's a plugin
where text and Ascii symbols
are generated from videos or images,
and they transform data into visual
poetry.
So in the top left
picture one, see
an example of that
and is the originals or untitled work
that could be a segment based
and a read only text.
So after that
I arrive on to the practice
based based research and I create.
I have created a document log
that if you want, I can send
after that
about 25 pages of resources and stuff.
That is really useful to learn both Python
and to learn and touch the signer.
A derivative has some courses, and also
I checked a lot of youth tutorials,
and that was the time I spent at the end
for the acceleration
of my final digital poem.
I only spent five hours,
so it's like really sort of time.
But I had to prepare a lot for IMS.
And we have here
MCP architectural model, context protocol.
That is the architecture that allowed me
to work together with the project and the
AI, AI model that I
thought I wanted to create a poem,
and that's the one I wrote.
It's in the left, is in Galician
because it's my native language
and in the right
you said an English translation,
but it's not a really good English,
because a really good translation,
because it
eliminated all, all of the of the runs.
And then we have something about
what is like learning Python.
And I just want to state
that the community of this program
is really amazing.
They have a lot
of courses, a lot of tutorials, open
and free to use, and derivatives.
The company
sets meetups
for the people to create together.
And for example, in this Austin designer
meetup,
people got to see the poet engineer
the artist.
I told you before
and it was like really interesting.
And it's a really a wealthy community.
And then, okay,
this is the AI setup that I used.
I tried a lot of things.
First of all, I wanted to try local
AI because I was more concerned
about the quality and about sizes,
but my computer is not that good,
so it can support a really good local AI,
and I try those different combinations
at the end.
And the best one was using in the cloud.
That still has privacy.
And it's not a really big corp
in that sense.
Like like like OpenAI for example.
And.
Okay.
And thank you for the minutes.
And then I used a continue
that is an extension for visual codes.
And that allows us to load our model
and top to our model
directly from from VS code
and allows us to
to interact
with the model context protocol.
The model context protocol
that I used was a boy.
That is a really a really great protocol
for touch designer
because it allows us to it allows the
it allows the
the model to see and to create
and to move things inside of the work.
And we can we can literally check
we can literally see the model
moving things and creating things
according to the things
that we write to it.
And for that I tried with the free coder,
but at the end the best one was the GLM.
That is a really
a really new or recent model,
and that that works
really good
with such complicated tasks. And
yes, that this is my main.
So my setup like we are going to like sit
quit because I don't have much time left.
So in the in
the picture that is in the down side,
we can see like the MCP service
connected to the local, the model in
in continue inside VS code.
And here we can see it working.
I asked it Rona query
my network unleashed my ops,
my different nodules that I have in in
and it's checked.
And those are literally
the ops that I really has.
And now
yes, I have here some observations,
some final remarks.
But before I wanted to.
So the work that I did so I will
I will be showing a different screen.
This one I made a video.
Of this of mean trading with the work.
So I hope it's running.
This is the the way that a user can see it
as the center.
And my work is the thing
that it's in the background.
So here we have different nodes.
And in a matter of seconds
we will be set work hopefully.
The thing was if I enjoy my fingers
the poem appears and if I let my fingers
go, the poem disappears.
And when my fingers are pinched,
you can see that the video goes
really slower.
Like almost like
I think it's four times slower.
And when I let them go, it goes faster.
And it also detects some particular forms
in the background
that make those strange squares.
And you can see here
the media pipe plugin working.
And yes,
that was this.
And I
will just say my final remarks
and I will be over with it.
So of course
I arrive at the
at the obviously conclusion that that's
the center is an application with great
potential for developing digital poetry.
It was really easy to create the
the the digital poem.
It was not really easy
to arrive at the correct
AI model, MCP, MCP set up
and was really complicated
because you need to get
because I hadn't it.
You need to get a lot of knowledge
about how to work
and how to how to work with AI.
And and also the problem with
the technical debt is not fixed.
So this, this, this alternative
like not going to GDP
and writing make appointments
but using as a tool the digital
then artificial intelligence to okay
one more sentence and I am so using.
Using digital
artificial intelligence to assist us
in the creation of digital poems,
reduces the technical debt and
allows an open and opens
a really big avenues for innovation
and for a creation that are not,
that are not served.
For a
person that knows anything about code
or only a little bit like me.
And and yes, I think that's so.
Thank you all for being here.
And thank you
also for the to the organization.